hey Brandon Sanderson here welcome to
the 2025 lecture series these are
lectures that I give at my local
University Brigham Young University
about Science Fiction and Fantasy
writing every week I'm going to have a
new one for you this week we're doing
mostly introductory material I'm going
to talk about um My Philosophy in
teaching this class I'm going to talk
about the difference between a discovery
writer and an outline writer I'm going
to talk about a lot of interesting sort
of philosophy of how to approach being a
writer with the eye toward being a
professional as long as we're in this
class it's not how you have to do it but
it's what I'm going to assume for the
hours that you're here with me so join
me here and then uh I will see you back
every week hopefully for another lecture
hey welcome to class I I surprised
[Applause]
[Music]
you uh this is how to write Science
Fiction and Fantasy
uh if you're not here for Science
Fiction and Fantasy well you can stay uh
we'll convert you we love having you
here um
so what this class is is Brandon
lectures at you for approximately an
hour and a half I believe um and we
started this up with it being kind of a
normal 218 class how to write science
fiction fantasy the class burgeoned
it grew um as my notoriety grew to
eventually the point that people were
packing in we had to move to lecture
hall hey how you doing um uh I'm doing
all right so these days it really is and
this is this is how I run it a lecture
series now after this there is the the
second class I should have my 15 16 this
sweet year people here who are in that
class that's the by application one only
we'll figure out what we're doing with
you afterward uh and the rest of you
you're welcome to apply for that class
that one's by application only uh and we
do it every year after this class so
what are we going to do in this class
well I am going to come every week and I
am going to turn on a fire hose of
information right and I'm going to blast
you with this fire hose of information
and you're going to try to drink some of
it and that which you can't drink you
can hopefully come back and get on the
videos that we are posting this year on
YouTube so you're being
recorded not much of you only your
laughter and maybe the backs of some of
your heads um that's why we're in this
new fancier room we have a camera that's
to capturing their faces oh your faces
are on the camera
[Applause]
[Music]
too you should have had to sign a thing
that says we're going to make you
internet famous
Nate uh by the way who here took the
class last year uh those who were here
last year Nate finished a
[Applause]
book Nate finished the second book
he's actually finished three which means
he's one off from running a
[Applause]
Kickstarter joking joking joking uh so
um I might uh I might make some of you
so anyway last year he had uh expressed
uh that he had trouble as many authors
do um getting really into a project
starting to write and then losing
momentum and revising the same chapter
over and over again and never finishing
anything am I paraphrasing it right Nate
uh and so um I started checking up on
him every week and embarrassing him in
front of class and he was a very good
sport um so I'm happy to see you back
and congratulations well done um so hey
you're back too aren't you yeah yeah
good to see you um some of you I
recognize some of you do I recognize you
yeah people take the class so often you
guys intimidate hey they're all up here
hey I recognize though that's that's
scar uh you even know my name I you
probably don't remember I totally know
your
name l l that's right El I told you I
was going to remember your name I
promised I would at some point uh so put
me in a whole book yeah welcome L you
told me that last time too I spelled it
differently though no no it's say it's e
l e not just the letter okay well
welcome L good to see you again um so uh
we will have lots of people running
around doing video recordings ignore
them pretend they're not here uh so what
do we got well because you're get we're
getting recorded this year I'm going to
try to do better to write on the board
what we're going to talk about each week
and then actually keep to
it we'll see how much I deviate from
that um with various tangents which I do
love and enjoy um but we are going to
approach this class um from a sort of
we'll talk about this later a nuts and
bolts approach this shouldn't hopefully
uh ruin your artistic expression in fact
it should help elevate it we'll talk
about that we are going to spend two
weeks each on plot setting character and
The Business of writing all right those
are kind of our core ideas that we'll
cover um I'm usually gone at least one
week and I bring in guest
lecturers um in the past G guest
lectures have been people to focus on
short story writing um or on Indie
publishing uh and I'll try to get
somebody like that who can cover a realm
of publishing that uh from a from from a
place of more expertise right uh because
on one metric I'm the most successful
Indie published author ever but that's
metric was trading on my already
established traditionally published name
um so I usually we we'll see what
happens um that week so that'll cover uh
nine of our weeks several of our other
weeks will be Q&A sessions usually what
I like to do is I like to have um two
weeks on say plot and then a Q&A on plot
two weeks on setting then a Q&A on
setting two weeks on character Q&A two
weeks on business Q&A right um and that
should basically cover the class um in
there somewhere I do tend to try to
squeeze in many lectures on
revision uh and a mini lecture on Pros
so we'll see what we can do uh with
those sorts of things but let's talk
about the the the beginning idea My
Philosophy for this class what is My
Philosophy for teaching and for teaching
writing in particular because writing is
kind of hard to teach not to make my job
sound more cool because it's kind of
hard to teach because you will learn
more than I can teach you in this class
hey how you doing
um by writing your first book then
myself or any person can possibly teach
you right writing as an art requires
work and effort everything requires work
and effort but the thing about a lot of
artistic Pursuits like this is you need
to start exploring with your style hey
you're back too good to see you um
exploring with your style seeing how it
goes trying new things revising uh
trying different things and as you
explore writing you will get better and
better and you will know how to use the
tools that people like myself give you
you will also know which tools to
ignore because one of the key
philosophies I have is writing advice is
only as good good as its ability to help
you
individually you will get bad advice for
you you will get bad advice for you from
me in this class okay I try hard not to
give you too much of that but the thing
is writing is so individual that works
for some what works for some writers
doesn't work for others for example the
one I I often use because it hit me when
I was young uh and I was working I was
reading um a book by Orson Scott Card
where he talked about writing and in it
he talked a lot about how important an
outline was to his writing and without
it his writing would become a disaster I
then later read an essay by Stephen King
may have even been on in on writing his
famous writing book where he talks about
how an out outline is the great
destroyer of
stories and if you have uh an outline
for your story it's going to ruin your
story and these are Polar Opposites
right um and can you do both well the
answer is yes most everyone in this room
is going to be some mix of what George R
Martin calls a gardener versus an
architect he's very good with words and
that's one of his descriptions that I
love he says some writers are an
architect they build themselves a
structure for for their story like a
house and then they hang a Story upon it
other writers he says are like a
gardener they go out in the garden and
they nurture something as it starts to
grow and then they see what it
becomes um you might have heard the term
pancing for writing people use that uh
the truth is that most writers are
somewhere in between those two extremes
but you won't know where you are and
indeed what a given project requires
until you try both of them and make your
own Frankenstein monster of a style and
a process out of the things that
everyone tells you and which you
discover on your own and that monster
will grow and change through your career
and you will do different things so why
am I sometimes going to give you bad
advice well it's because it works for
90% of authors but you're the 10% or it
might be the advice that is good for you
20 years from now when you've changed as
an author and you're like hey I remember
that thing let's try that but right now
it could be
destructive our philosophy My
Philosophy is to treat you
like a chef and not a
cook um those who' have been in this
class before know I love this metaphor
what does this metaphor mean well in my
definitions a chef is someone like me
when it comes to baking who can follow a
recipe and if I follow the wet recipe
usually I'll get what I'm trying to make
and it usually tastes something like
what I'm trying to
make the problem is if something goes
wrong I have no idea why it went wrong
and what I could have done to change it
I have no idea what temperature does to
baking only that on this page it says
bake it at 325 and if I do that it
usually turns
out I don't know the difference between
baking soda and baking powder except on
the page it says use one and not the
other and if you mix them up it's bad
right um that is what I will term a cook
what is is a chef chef is a person who
can tell you well when you add this
ingredient it does this a chef is a
person who can taste something and be
like oh this is what went wrong let's
try it this way next time and see if it
improves it a chef is someone who can
take the various styles of baking that
different people use and apply them to
their own process and create new things
not from a recipe but that use the
knowledge of previous recipes to create
masterful new works I want you to be a
chef when it comes to writing I want you
to learn all the tools and processes I
want you to try them I want you to work
with them and as you do learn how to
create the effect you want to have with
your stories as you write and finish
them rather than the effect other people
say you should
have your goals can be your own and I'm
slightly out of a order here because
let's talk about being a Pro versus
being a non-pro writer it is okay in
fact it is wonderful to be a
nonprofessional
writer um you can be in this class for
any reason you could have wandered in
accidentally seen that there were people
here and taken a seat you
weirdo right you're welcome you're
welcome here um you can be here because
you're like that's Sanderson guy maybe
if I take his class I'll get a book
signed you shouldn't be doing that but
I'll make you learn learn
anyway and so it's good for you um you
might be here because you're like well I
need to have a certain number of writing
credits and um you know this is the
class that's in the evening that I can
take you might be here because you want
to be a better
GM you might be here because you just
love the process or you might be here as
the majority of you probably are is
because you're like maybe I could become
a professional science fiction fantasy
writer those are all valid reasons to be
here I would guess the most the balance
the the most common is those who want to
be a pro and those who would like to
learn to write a good book now and then
as a hobby uh those are my most common
students wonderful I think writing is
good for you um and one of the things
you're going to have to
confront when you're writing stories and
you tell people about it they're going
to ask you a
question have you been asked this
question what is it are you are you
published what are you going to do with
this how soon till you can take me out
to dinner with the money you make from
your
books right um we live in a society that
likes to approach things from a
utilitarian eye there are advantages to
that right there are advantages to my
mother when I was 16 discovering that I
wanted to be a writer and
saying that's nice dear you should be a
doctor and I'm like but do she's like
doctors have a lot of free time you know
how doctors are always golfing right
well you could be a doctor who writes
fantasy novels instead of golfing and
also feed your
family she really wanted a doctor and
she got none out of her four children oh
no yeah no doctors no doctor she got me
um she got my brother who's in computer
programming that's close to being a
doctor he got the closest she got a
teacher um and she got an artist
slfashion designer SL charity
organizer that's Jane who runs
lightweaver for me um and so she got no
doctors uh she got none married to
doctors but she loves us
anyway there is an advantage to people
saying that because you do need to ask
those questions right
um but our society treats art too
utilitarian um it doesn't look at the
primary purpose of art which is making
the artist's life more enriched as
sincerely what I believe the primary
purpose is it is to make your life
better by creating something when you go
play basketball unless you have to H
happen to have a Wes height
people are probably not going to ask you
after your game in the you know the
church gym uh and you're like oh I get
you know and you maybe look more like me
then and they're not going to say so
when are you going to the
NBA uh they just they won't but they
will ask you when you're going to sell
your writing they're going to ask you uh
if you're
published and that's okay but I want you
to understand that's not why you have to
write
in fact it's probably not why you should
write writing is good for you expressing
yourself is good for you creating art is
good for
you that all said we are going to
pretend when you walk through those
doors that every one of you is in the
category that I mentioned that wants to
be making a full-time living as a
Science Fiction and Fantasy novelist
within the next 10
years the reason for that is all the
other advice that I would give you to be
a better GM or to have a what be better
at writing in your journal or to be to
be fulfilled as writing a book every 20
years or every five years for your
sisters like Jane Austin did all of that
advice is circumscribed in the advice I
would give to the aspiring professional
and I want to give you all the possible
tools that I can so that you can be
become that professional if someday you
decide that you want
to but let's take a moment to look at it
realistically probably the only time in
this class that we will do
that making a living as a professional
novelist or as a professional musician
working on kind of the highest uh record
label touring level um or as a fine
artist not working in uh you know in
commercial illustration these jobs are
hard not that they're any harder to do
than other types of jobs but they are
harder to make a living at than other
kinds of the job of jobs um as a writer
there are lots of options open to you
I'm sure the university will tell you
what they are scar wrote for a hearing
egg company uh for how many years 10 10
years 10 years wrote copy in the hearing
a company for their for their hearing a
books about you know how to operate the
hearing how to operate the hearing aids
you can tell the enthusiasm in his
voice um by the way if you don't know
scar scar Works uh at Dragon steel uh he
is my uh one of my executive assistance
Becky is the other one she's back there
um so they are here to facilitate making
things uh happen and to get me in the
place where I'm supposed to be at the
time I'm supposed to be
there um Dan uh went on Dan friend of
mine he wrote for the newsletter for a
scrapbooking company there are lots of
those kinds of
jobs writing fiction and making a living
at it is hard now it's not as hard as
they told me when I took this uh was
taking classes like this when I was
young it's not as hard as my mom thought
she would have told you it's one in a
million if you'd ask other people to be
like you know one in 10,000 whatever um
I took this class in
1999 yeah I know I used to think of
myself as the young guy now this is the
young people over here when I I took
this class in 99 from Dave Wolverton who
has since passed on um in that class was
myself Dan wels who went on to become a
professional novelist um and Stacy who
became a professional editor
and Peter who became a professional
editor as well as two people I would
list as semi-pros but there's four Pros
in that class of around 30 people okay
uh that's pretty good my odds have
generally been in my 15 person class one
to a half of a person every year going
pro depending on your definition of
going pro um more than one will get a
book published professionally but one to
to a half uh of one a year so one every
two years will go on to make a
significant portion of their living from
writing is about the odds that we have
had um jansy took my class and she went
uh full Pro Brian mlen uh took my class
he went full Pro there's a bunch of them
I can't list them all right now um
that's not because I'm such a great
teacher I hope that I'm good but it's
more along the lines of if you are
seriously dedicated to this and willing
to invest 10 years in it you probably
got more like a one in 20 shot of uh of
making a significant uh portion of your
income from writing than a one in a
million now that
does not count the fact that um a lot of
people are going to give up before then
so it's probably less than one in uh
better than one in 20 but you know
um that's better odds Than People
pretend right you would not have thought
that uh let's acknowledge that of the
people that went pro that are my friends
or in that
class only one of them is regularly
hitting the New York Times bestseller
list right um but you can make a living
without doing that or significantly
contribute to your to your income let
that
said if you went and took a class in the
computer science department and the
professor got up and said I think maybe
one in 20 of you can actually make some
of your living at this maybe one in 50
fully on
professional um are going to be able to
you would
leave right you would be like I am going
to chemical
engineering oh the they have a 90
something per placement rate right do
you guys know what it is it used to be
the highest at BYU which is why I use
that one as a joke are you chemical
Engineers my uh called freshman roommate
uh was a chemical engineer uh uh if
you've ever read the mistform books
Captain Conrad is based off of Tom
Conrad good friend of mine still he went
on to work for Intel he is a
glorified seage treatment plant engineer
he right because he cleans their water
for Intel that's his job he loves
cleaning water he gets all he gets the
dirty water and he figures how to
separate all the stuff out that you can
sell for money and then make the rest of
the stuff non-toxic so you can then
dispose of it or purify it so that they
can be used uh that's Tom's job he's
very good at it um but it's good to
bring up chemical engineering because
when I was in school in this class
taking this class Tom was getting put
through the ringer you people I'm so
sorry he would come back and be
like I got a 61 on my test and I'd be
like you know I'm in the Arts right like
we we don't look at those numbers and
he's and and and he's like oh no I was
second highest in the
class yeah we talked about sonnets and
shared our feelings and all got
Ace so
um
but if you want to be going pro in the
next 10 years you're going to have to
pretend you're in the chemical
engineering department but for
writing so our My Philosophy again is to
encourage an aggressive for whatever
your definition that is writing
schedule during your early years in
order for you to learn your
process your job as a writer right now
if you have not finished at least three
novels I'm just pulling that out of the
air it could be but let's just go with
that if you haven't finished at least
three maybe if you haven't finished five
I saw sold my sixth Dan sold his sixth
you sold your seventh um right um if you
haven't you know if you haven't done you
know that many that's that's not where
you are your job is not to sell
books even if you want to be a
professional your job is to write enough
books to learn your process and what
works for you and this is where the bad
viice comes in once in a while there's a
stupid Pat rothus who writes a brilliant
book their first time
and then revises it a ton because he did
sweat in Te if you know Pat he revised
it maybe uh to insane levels but once in
a while there's a stupid Pat rfus who's
brilliant at the start and just writes a
really great book um Harry Potter was
the first book Twilight was the first
book name of the wind was the first
book launchers was my sixth mistborn was
my
14th um I find a lot more those than I
find of your first book and most the
people I know whose first book get got
published kind of wish that they had
then written several more books before
they published it so that when they
published that first book they already
knew their
style so that when the weight of
deadlines hit
them they already were practiced at
consistently writing and that for if you
are so lucky as to get published you're
suddenly going to have deadlines you're
suddenly going to have to write while
the entire world is critiquing what
you've
done you're somehow going to have to
keep writing as you stress about whether
or not your books are selling any copies
and worrying they're not selling enough
copies and trying to deal with publicity
and trying to deal with all of the
headaches and heartaches that come from
being a professional and if you have not
spent years practicing so that writing
and the habits of it are
secondhand that part is so much harder
so very much harder I um so if you have
not
finished several novels let's say um I
Heard early on that your first five
books are generally crap and it was good
advice for me because I said oh I don't
have to stress about this for five books
and I wrote five books and they were
mediocre and I said I love Epic fantasy
I've spent this time learning this and I
sat down I wrote aess and it sold still
took a couple years but it sold
um who knows was that the right there
was definitely right advice for me is it
right advice for you I don't know but
I'm telling you right now you should
probably approach your writing as you
might
approach playing the piano and your
first books are learning your scales
this can be really hard for some people
it can be really hard you know generally
for for for most people knowing that
this beautiful thing that you're working
on this this you have this baby that
you've cherished and you might uh you
might have cherished this baby since you
were a teenager meaning I'm going to
write this book someday and you might
have written in your books in school as
I did sketches of your characters and
ideas for plot lines for that book that
you're going to write and you may have
this book that built over many years and
you might run into the situ situation
upon writing it that suddenly your baby
is
ugly it's here and it's ugly and what do
you do oh no and it's even worse than
the baby being ugly you know the baby is
actually well the baby was perfect in
your mind this book it was gorgeous and
beautiful and then you made it ugly
through your fat fingers being unable to
accomplish what you want to
accomplish very deadly to new writers
because they get stopped because their
skill isn't up to their aspirations yet
you need to push through that and keep
writing you need to learn early on that
the product of your writing time is
yourself you are the
artwork the time you spend writing will
change you it will make you better
expressing your ideas it will make you
um you'll have a wonderful time it's
just wonderful writing but you will also
grow as a person you will become more
empathetic all these things will happen
to you the product of your writing time
is you you are the piece of art now as
you get better and better at that that
time spent making yourself better does
start producing things that hopefully
you can
sell my philosophy um on artistic
expression is while you are writing the
book The Artist should be in
control you should be making the
decisions that the artist thinks are
genuinely the best decisions for that
story and those
characters the moment you finish that
book there should be a second person
inside of you who takes the artist
shoves them in a closet locks the door
takes the manuscript and runs away
cackling and then figures out every
mercenary way to exploit that book for
profit that is legal in our
system so that you can let that person
back out and they will have enough you
know food to eat so they can go and be
ar the next time that's the perspective
you'll take in the class go could should
the second person worry about how the
the the artist feels about what they've
done with yes you you you definitely
should um I'm being a little
exaggerating that your Artistic
integrity uh maintains you are the same
person right there are certain things
that you will not do as an artist with
your book and that's you know yes
absolutely right um I'm just talking
about this idea of the business person
shouldn't be in charge when you're
writing but as you finish the book
learning the business and letting the
business person take charge is a good
idea but yeah they definitely do not
compromise your Artistic integrity
through revisions because of what the
business person thinks um but sometimes
you might let me give you an example
John schaly wanted to be a novelist uh
he's a very good writer good friend of
mine um he had been a blogger for a long
time he decided I'm going to be a
novelist so he went to the bookstore
and he said what's selling right now he
picked up a few books and said these
look like they're selling I'll write one
of these and then he went home and then
the artist took over and he wrote one of
those I wouldn't say that John
compromised his Artistic integrity but
there definitely was a back and forth
between the business person and the
artist when it came to choosing that
project right uh and how he chose to
release it and sell it and things like
that so there there definitely I think
there should be communication between
the two sides of your brain but I do
think that letting the artist make the
artistic decisions and letting the
business person then learn how to sell
that book rather than to dictate what
book what the book should be is
generally the way you want to go once in
a while that's bad advice it might have
been bad advice for John right uh other
questions on what I've said so far yeah
go ahead our first books are not should
we spend a lot of time revising yes but
here's why revision is
uh a difficult skill to learn on par
with learning to write a book I learned
while I was not selling books um and
getting very close I learned a lesson
that some of my friends who were
creating the best artwork were better
revisers than they were
writers um and I might if I were you
like there's an argument to just putting
aside the first book and then writing
the second one and then coming back
later and maybe revising the first or
maybe not even ever touching the first
but the truth is a lot of people's
second books are publishable it might be
better if you think you're going to
write five and then publish number two
um but most people wish they'd written a
couple even if they are starting off a
genius and revision is a really
important thing to learn I would say the
reason it took me um as long as it did
to sell a launchess after I wrote it uh
because it came out in 2005 and I wrote
it in 98 um was because I hadn't learned
revision I would write those first five
books I never did a second draft I wrote
them and then you know I figured I'd
always the next book would be better so
why not just write that this is a
classic I'm more of an outliner this
happens more often to outliners than it
does to Discovery writers um that they
think well I've decided by the next book
I'm going to go WR that Discovery
writers have the opposite problem they
do tend to over revise they write a
chapter and then they revise it and they
write a chapter and then they revise it
and they go back and revise the first
one again and then they write chapter 3
and then they revise the other two and
then now they need to do this revise
chapter 3 now and then they never get
anywhere um oh we've got another Nate up
there your name isn't Nate is
it uh because this is funny because last
year I was telling a story like this and
I had a guy in my writing group whose
name was Nate who did this and this
guy's like I do that my name is
Nate so um so this does tend to be more
of a a problem but uh I will say those
writers who who constantly rise the
early chapters they don't tend to make
it has been my experience because um
having 80 first chapters doesn't get you
very far now you could be a fantastic
short story writer um short stories
don't earn any money anymore so it's
really hard to make a living short story
writing fact kind of impossible unless
you're also doing lecture series and
being a professor um so yeah uh so yes
learn revision it's really important by
the way you were in the class before too
weren't you good to see you um all right
we'll go here and then we'll get some in
the back so when you first started
writing and you weren't good at it what
was it do you think especially like you
know when you knew you had to practice
and spend free time when you could be
you know doing something else what was
it that that got you to go back and
write okay what made me write uh what
gave me the motivation there's a couple
of things so when I was brand new at
this
um I saw that if I didn't learn to write
I was going to have to get a job that I
did not enjoy as much because I
genuinely enjoyed writing um so I came
to BYU as a chemical
engineering actually is bioengineering
but you know yeah yeah some something uh
because my my mother convinced me that
um that Engineers got I was biochemistry
that's what it was the engineers got
scholarships and she still wanted a
doctor so badly uh and they I came to
viu and they threw me in the weeder
classes for chemistry which I actually
really appreciate because they taught me
I did not want to be doing chemistry
every day right oh boy did I not want to
be doing chemistry uh I went uh on a
mission to Korea and I'm like I'm I'm on
a different Cent from chemistry oh it's
so nice
um but writing when I would sit down to
write hours could pass and I wouldn't
know what time it was that doesn't mean
that writing was easy right usually
starting is hard uh or if I hit a rough
patch you know I would still give up or
things like that so I still needed this
motivation but that was a key sign to me
that I love the busy work of writing so
much more than other things so good sign
there that I um and so the thing that
worked best for me is that I would start
keeping a spreadsheet with the per the
mount I'd written each day and my goal
and if I hit my goal then I didn't have
to worry about it anymore I was making
the progress that I needed to and I
could go play Halo right I could go do
whatever I wanted because I had hit my
goal for the day uh and a lot of times I
made it such a go a goal that it was a
little difficult to hit but not
impossible it wasn't actually hard it
was just like I had to actually work
most days I would double that goal right
because it was a goal that it was it was
something like a thousand words um right
uh enough that I actually had to sit
down and do it but once I got into it I
would keep going um and then I got I
said put that in my spreadsheet and I
watched those numbers counting up and it
worked for me like the progress bar in a
MMO for getting your next level worked
I'm like hey I will hit 25% soon wow I
will hit 50 I'm almost done and that
every day um was a balance of making me
feel like man I've gotten my work done I
can relax I don't have to stress about
this my job right now isn't to publish
books my job is to write those first
five books and to do and to learn from
them so if I today have hit my thousand
words I'm on my I'm on my path that I've
done basically all that I can do
realistically with my me you know a
normal person's mental health and things
like that in order to hit that goal in
10 years and it worked um granted I'm
going to get to your question up
here let's talk about survivorship
bias we're in this this year so I think
every person entering into a creative or
even a professional field needs to know
about uh survivorship bias because there
are a whole lot of grifters out there
who Coast on survivorship bias
survivorship bias is our brains are more
likely to weigh the words of someone
who's been
successful even if their success was
random than someone who has not been if
we didn't know that flipping coins was
random and we had a competition in
everyone one in here flip coins until we
had one person left that flipped heads
the whole time everyone in this room
would be asking them for advice next
time and indeed they may go on the guru
circuit earning big money writing books
about flipping coins and about how you
do it and their process and they might
even name it and come up with a YouTube
course that you can pay for right um
that's survivorship bias we cannot say
whether what contributed to my success
the this is why I try to give you lots
of tools right that worked for me I am a
survivor of that system working who
knows right but that's the best I can
give you so I like the way you phrase
your question what for me kept me going
and that's what kept me going now
something else you need to hear about
what time is
it that's 7:46 7:46 we go to 8:30 8:15
okay all right I got time left hey I got
another class uh but we've gotten
through almost all of this
um so I can I can do lots of questions
let's tell you the story of Brandon
almost giving up some of you heard this
story
before I am in this story applying to
grad schools and getting rejected from
all of
them um NYU rejected Columbia rejected
Iowa rejected everybody rejected me um I
had written at the time
around 12
novels and I hadn't sold any my father
would call me and give me Father speak
for I'm very concerned by saying son
your mother's very
concerned father speak little
interpretation for you if you ever get
that
um they were worried both of them that I
was going to end up begging for beans on
the side of the road because instead of
becoming a doctor I had decided to be a
science fiction novel
um and they were kind of right right
like I talked about it earlier having a
backup plan is a good idea in a career
where one out of 20 talented people who
work very hard for 10 years are going to
make a living right 19 of them won't and
jansy will tell you that it took her
even after she started selling books
over a decade to start earning what
people would consider even close to a
income right um I think the first year
that she made uh she said she made
enough to live on by itself with her
writing was the year she co-authored the
book with
me um and she is very good at
self-publishing she knows her stuff um
so it's good to have a backup plan right
and I didn't have
one I had decided to eventually I got
into BYU grad program right I did Begin
by everyone else rejected me I went
through one round of all the top schools
they all rejected me then I went to the
second tier schools and BYU and of them
only B why you let me in uh for grad
school you don't usually want to go to
grad school in the same place that you
went undergrad which is why I applied
everywhere else first uh but I was only
applying to the schools that I would if
I got a degree from I could then go on
to get a job you know as a writer
because BYU at the time didn't have an
MFA and MFA was considered the degree
you needed to be a professional teacher
in creative writing getting a masters
from BYU in creative writing actually my
parents didn't know it at that point
would not do anything for me becoming a
professor it was virtually useless as
they stepped being a professor because
it wasn't an MFA wasn't a masters of
Fine Arts they now have one and their
program uh has gained reputation because
of that uh so those who are in it now
don't panic um but back then it it it
really couldn't do anything that said
Andy was in my class and she's a
professor of BYU right now and she's
really good so I don't think she got an
MFA though did she or did she go back
and get one she was in my class when it
was when we didn't we didn't get the F
we just had an ma um so I got into BYU
but my parents are calling me and I'm
like oh man I'm
stallin um what am I doing with my life
I can't teach I went to a class um the
first day at uh in University as a as a
creative writing major and Lance was
teaching the class anyone here did Lance
retire does anyone know if Lance retired
Lance Larson he's still here you said he
retired you're
wrong haha okay
sorry Lance was the poet laureate of
Utah um he's very good teacher uh very
good poet uh he was uh in charge of
graduate students in the master's
program in creative writing or in just
the masters of English program and he
got up in the first day of kind of your
here you're a grad student now let's
talk about it and said he pulled out a
thing he said here is the CV which is
kind of like the resume for students for
those who online who might not know of
someone who got into a top tier school
for a PhD to go and went on and became a
professor in English and it went to the
floor right said they were on every
Journal they worked with this many
professors on these and they they spent
something like you know 40 hours a week
outside of school working in order to
build their CV so they could get into a
school so that school can then propel
them into a career that's what you're
going to need to do if you want to
become a professor um uh at a
prestigious University um with a on a
10year track and I looked at that and I
said cannot write books and do
that so I'm not going to do
that and I didn't um
but I didn't have a backup right uh and
I kind of had to that moment confront
what do I do
right do I give up do I go get a real
job I was working at a hotel's a
graveyard shift so I could write at work
right overnight um worked very well for
me it was bad advice for Isaac who tried
to do that friend of mine who's now at
my company uh he tried to do the same
thing and he is not a night person and
it did not work for
him um so I looked at this and I thought
am I going to stop writing and looking
seriously and honestly at my heart I
said
no whatever I end up doing I'm not going
to stop writing this is who I am I'm
going to keep writing and if I'm aged
90 and I never sell a book and my books
are only for my family and my friends
then I'm
success that's the success I can control
and I'm going to do that um now I've
been doing everything I was supposed to
do I've been submitting but people this
was when George first got big and Grim
dark was the new hotness right Brandon
is not Grim dark I tried it was not I I
tried writing Grim dark and it turned
into the story of a grim Dark Assassin
who found Hope and
love I'm not even kidding right um like
just Grim dark and not my thing um and
so you know darkness in a world great
but um but not my thing so I'm like I
can't you know and so I sat down and
said well they keep telling me the
Publishers keep telling me I'm writing
books too long uh they wanted shorter
books where they really they're really
hunting those of you who know your
history of fantasy they wanted George's
aesthetic but they wanted it to be
cheaper to publish right the bigger the
book you can't so here's some economics
of books for you a
400,000 word book which is the length of
the storm light books and um The Game of
Thrones is even longer sometimes um
right that that is four times more
expensive to edit four times more
expensive to uh well maybe not four
times but significantly more expensive
to print significantly more expensive to
ship and to the bookstores it's four
times of the 100,000 word book more
expensive to put on the Shelf because if
you can put three books on the shelf or
one book which one do you want to put on
the shelf right the problem is the way
that economics of entertainment work in
our world is you don't charge much more
for longer entertainment movies cost
about the same no matter what length
they are books maybe go up a buck but a
Stormlight book should probably like if
a normal paperback is eight books bucks
a Stormlight book in paperback should
for the amount of like money and time
and all these things should probably
cost like 25 but we can't do that and so
they don't like long books they're
better with them now that ebooks are a
thing but audiobooks still you know know
more expensive to Bruce anyway they
wanted Joe abber cromy they wanted
George like Grim dark aesthetic but
short and I was I was like the worst for
them then right I was long and I was
like hopeful epic aesthetic right the
big hotness was low magic uh and I was
like there's 30 magic systems right like
and this is the era where people didn't
even use the word magic system the same
way they do now they didn't know what to
do with me um and and so I'm getting I
got all these directions like I remember
walking up to someone dired me I'm like
thank you for the direction do you have
any advice CU a form rejection he said
read the first chapter of Game of
Thrones write something like that see
Steve sapple at uh at Del Rey that's
exactly what he told me um and so it's
like whatever so I'm like all right I'm
going to write what I want I'm not going
to care I'm going to write they tell me
to run sure I'm going to write the
biggest Dar book all right they tell me
Realo magic no no no uh right uh and I
wrote I wrote The Way of Kings Way of
Kings Prime right and as I was finishing
that book is when aant sold um and I
still remember that kind of you know
that belly of the whale if you want to
use your writing metaphors that long
dark tea time of the
Soul um dirt gently um Douglas Adams
quote there um that moment was really
really helpful for me because I had gone
through making the hard decision that I
was going to write for the rest of my
life before I became one of the most
famous writers in the world uh and that
was really handy to have made that
decision before I sold and things like
that so tangents I warned you about
those we got we got time left all right
question back there hit hit me I'm going
to do I'm going to do a rapid fire round
I'm GNA actually do them fast um if
you're too attached to a world built and
don't want to like put all the effort to
jump ship and World build a new thing
and plan all these new things yeah you
say it's detrimental or is it fine to
still write like five books but in the
same setting or the same I think that's
good that's great uh totally worth doing
uh the question is let's say you want
you want to write five books um but you
don't want to abandon all your world
building totally okay to write those all
in the same world now what I would tell
you is there's a Gambit for you here all
right um You can do a Sanderson and you
can write five different books with five
different protagonists just you can
share some of the it's more like a an an
maccaffrey um she used to do this and
things like that or you can do a Tamar
rare Tamar rare she wrote four of those
I think maybe three four straight in a
series those were her you know she just
wrote those books without selling any of
them now why this is a Gambit is you
cannot send book two of a series to an
editor or sell it to um to Indie
publishing until you've you know like
they reject book one you can't send them
book two but if they're in the same
world you can but if it's a sequel you
can't she put her all her eggs in her
back the same basket but then when
tamare sold the Publishers knew they had
gold on their hands CU they had three
finished books and maybe a fourth so
they put just an enormous marketing
campaign behind that uh that you won't
understand how big a deal this is
because you're all young uh but some of
you will who are not uh you know quite
so quite so young her cover blurbs on
her first three books were Ste King an
mcaffrey and Terry
Brooks they sent all of them all three
books and they're like all three are
done well I'm going to read them right
and they cover blured them it was
amazing and then she stomped me at the
Hugo awards for best new author uh
because of that and she deserved it um
so so anyway uh there's your Gambit uh
writing all in the same world but not
direct sequels is kind of the best of
both so if that's uh appeals to you
totally do that it's what it's what
Rachel did it worked for her so I was
wondering like if you have a world that
you're like incredibly proud of and you
can working on for like years and years
how do you escape like the track of like
having using the first like four or five
books to like throw away those so you
can get to that six okay so you've got a
world you've been working on you're so
excited by you don't want to throw it
away CU it's your baby uh you got a
couple of options number one is write
that first book get it out of your
system know that you're probably just
going to then come back and write it
better okay that's the one I kind of
recommend that way of Kings Prime didn't
sell it was there was stuff wrong with
it years later when I had more
experience I just wrote it over from
scratch and kind of having a book that
was a rough draft of the book I wanted
to write where I could see all the flaws
with my now experience and write a much
better version I didn't revise it I just
started on page one but it was almost
like I had an outline that was the wrong
version of the book was really handy and
it is part of why way of Kings is so
strong as a series is because I know
stuff about that world I don't know
about others because I wrote a whole
book that I threw away right so that's
what you can do but another thing people
do is they just they ideas are cheap
this is what you will learn as a writer
uh the ability to take ideas and make
them great and you're going to be my
last question so I'll get to you the
ability to take ideas and make them
great is uh is what people are looking
for two stories for you maybe one we'll
see how much time I have uh
so um there is a
writer um who he was hanging out on some
forums and he was arguing with some
people um and he took this stance
there's a new writer unpublished and he
said uh I think ideas are cheap and the
other person's like no no no ideas are
what makes science fiction fantasy if
you don't have good ideas then you got
nothing and the first writer's like I
tell you what give me your three three
worst
ideas or your two worst ideas it was two
I think uh I asked him this at dinner
and it's true so I'd heard it apocy
before but he confirmed it to me you can
ask him in person he said give me your
two burst ideas they said all right
Pokemon Meets The Lost Roman
legion and Jim
Butcher took that and he wrote a book
series called COA I heard it over here
they're fantastic in the hands of a
great writer great being someone who's
practiced a bunch you can take basically
any idea and you can make gold from it a
writer with bad with good ideas but not
the skill it's like playing piano that's
my other uh thing we mentioned playing
piano the other story is if we had
someone come up here who had been
practicing piano for a few months and
someone who had been practicing for 20
years how long do you think it would
take them to you to tell which is
which very very short amount of time
right it's the same thing in writing um
editors readers they can tell if you've
put that time into it so ideas are cheap
find some idea that just you know a
writing prompt mash it together with
another idea and add the plotline of a
film that you love that's in a different
genre and just write that book right
you're be like I'm going to write The
Godfather I love The Godfather except
it's mice and you know the magic system
is Magic cheese right uh and I'm going
to write write that book and then that
gives you your practice and you will
then discover that ideas kind of are
cheap uh and you get some practice and
then you save that book until later on
either of those are perfectly viable all
right last question um how do you get
make yourself get to point of of like
just rewriting a a story I've written
some some yeah how do you force yourself
to rewrite novels but like they need
rewrite but I don't know how to yeah
make myself do best uh so good question
how do you make yourself revise I am
there with you I hate revision it's my
least favorite part of everything the
whole process and that's why it took me
so long I am really good at revision
people hear this and they assume I'm bad
at it the things that you're bad at that
you have to force yourself to learn or
you will not be able to succeed
professionally tend to end up as your
strengths so that won't help you because
blah blah blah my weaknesses become
strengths yeah I know that's hard and I
don't want to do it right um so Burn
yeah yeah so
watch you need to uh well and helpful
for this is learning your um whether you
respond to carrots or sticks or
something else what makes you
consistently do the things you want to
have done right there's probably other
things in your life you want to have
done that you are able to get yourself
to do whether it's get up in the morning
whether it's go to the gym whether it's
read scriptures whatever it is what do
you have that you have built a habit out
of already and number one uh what made
you do that and number two can you
bundle your habits if there's something
you already do every day you're like
every day I go and I get my favorite
dirty Cola from the random dirty Cola
place that also sells cookies because
why not all the diabetes in one
place and I know I do that on the way
home from school I am going to stop in
that shop and I'm going to revise for
only only 30 minutes and then when I get
home I get to do something else that I
find fun well that that's what we call
kind of bundling when you group
something you don't want to do with
something you've already built a habit
to do so that the thing you don't want
to do but you want to have done also
becomes a habit um that works very well
learning whether you respond to you know
like for me counting up I can see the
percentages and small bites or whether
some people binge right like I don't
like revision so I'm going to take this
week that I'm off of school in the
summer and I only revise I don't get to
go do anything else I do it for 12 hours
a day then I Collapse and then at the
end of the week I'm done and I get to
take the summer off and then I'll start
writing a new book when uh fall semester
starts uh you have like your job as a
new writer is to figure out what
triggers these things and makes them
work in your mind helpful for me is to
make a revision guide if you're an
outliner naturally which you might be if
you don't like revision
having an outline for your revision that
has targeted goals kind of like have you
ever done any programming computer
programming a tiny tiny okay like okay
in Pro programming you might have a bug
list starting with your most important
bugs you're like in this book I've given
gotten feedback this character doesn't
work here's a plan for fixing the
character it's my most important thing
the main goal in this revision is to fix
that character if I have room in my
brain for a second goal here's the
second most important thing and I'm
going to find three places to foreshadow
this or to add a scene that fixes this
problem and then you do a revision
checking things off that list so you
feel like you're making accomplishments
and you're basically killing bugs in
your bug report that does tend to work
for some people as well particularly if
they are naturally an outliner having a
uh an outline but to do that you need to
get feedback and to get feedback we're
going to talk about writing groups segue
segue
welcome um so uh segue by the way I used
to think that you spelled that the that
s anyone wants have that was short for
segue and there was an actually a word
that was that plus way that was segue
and that the shortened version was seg
and you just say seg or people would
just write it uh right yeah anyone else
have this like why does that word say
segue
French engl French oh you Normans you
Normans came in you took our KN in your
Germanic leg language that like to
Crunch and kill and eat and you made it
instead so that we you know that we had
Rendevous and we didn't give up we
surrendered um and now we have two words
for everything one latinate and one
Germanic uh it's actually really good
for writers because the latinate words
naturally sound very uh upscale to us
and if you learn you know to watch for
the Germanic words because those were
the lower uh level words back in Middle
English era and the the uh the Norman
Latin words were the uh high class and
that's still around in uh in our
language so if you say I surrender that
indicates education if you say I give up
that indicates lower class you can use
that as a writer so it's actually a
useful thing so it's good but it is
annoying all right writing groups
writing
groups writing groups are for everyone
okay in fact writing groups can ruin
your
book learning to take feedback is
important for the majority of writers
writing groups are one of the ways that
you we can do that and I am able in my
class to do it in a controlled s uh
situation where it will not ruin
people's books I put a TA in every
writing group and I the TA knows how to
make sure that no one ruins each other's
books it is a good tool to try uh part
of this is uh part of the reason for
this
is when I took this class in 1999 I
formed a writing group with four people
me Dan Wells Peter Alstrom and
Ben Dan and I went on to become Pros he
sold um like he found an editor I sold
that editor and then he sold to that
editor and we both went full-time Peter
became a full-time editor at Tokyo pop
and then I hired him to be my editorial
VP at Dragon steel all three of us went
on to be pros and we are three of the
four people from that class who went on
to be
Pros now part of that is because I was
in this class and we were reading
writing samples and I zeroed in on Dan
and said he's a good writer I'm going to
put him in a writing group with me and
he said my friend Dan Ben wants to join
I'm like sure Ben's a CS guy he's our
friend he doesn't really write um but we
make fun of him on my podcast
um and then uh Peter was at the magazine
with us and I knew that Peter had a
really good editorial eye and I'm like
I'm G to put him in the uh writing group
because he's an editor and he knows what
he's doing so I specifically picked out
the two people in the class that I
thought were most likely to make it and
I formed a writing group with them and I
I was really good at that apparently of
picking them out right um but another
reason is for the same reason that
tolken and Lewis were in the same
writing group right um success breed
success writing groups from my class
that stick together often do give each
other help and legs up and things like
that so while writing groups aren't for
everyone I do think they're worth
trying so I'm going to give you today
the best inoculation against writing
groups ruining your writing so that you
can try them out if you would like and
then after this class if you would like
me to split you in this group into
writing groups I will do so all right if
you don't want to be in writing group
class then writing group then you can
leave and you can laugh at us all uh
with your other cool writing group with
cooler
friends so here's a couple of simple
rules that if you follow will help a ton
number one if you are a Discovery
writer be very careful about taking any
advice for your
book until after you have finished said
book and are working on a different
one this is because people who tend to
discover their
story can be taken over by the whims of
other people giving feedback too early
and Stephen King is the quintessential
Discovery writer one of the reasons he
doesn't like writing groups which he
doesn't is because they will do this to
him one of the reasons he doesn't like
outlines is because if he writes an
outline he feels like he's already
discovered the book and his enthusiasm
and excitement for that book vanishes
both perfectly valid ways to be a writer
but you this is why it's important to
understand these things right so if you
are a discovery writer try not to submit
too much or too early or if you do be
aware of what can happen if someone
hijacks your book I had someone in a
writing group once come and submit a
chapter and we gave some feedback and
they submitted another chapter and it
was wildly different but it was in the
same book and then the third chapter was
wildly different we're like so you were
writing a um a romance and now there's
vampires and she said yeah I took class
at BYU and the people in the class said
you know vampires would be really good
in this and they're selling really well
right now so I added them to the book
and the next one they're like oh it's
not exciting enough you know Thrillers
are doing well really well because the
um the D Vinci Code had just come out
and she was like well maybe I should
make this a thriller and her book was a
different book in every chapter writing
groups can do that to you okay now
you're warned about it hopefully that'll
inoculate you um number two if you are
getting feedback try not to say
anything this is really hard your job
getting feedback is to be a fly on the
wall while people are giving talking
about a story and write down what they
say in Hollywood they do this cool thing
where for years they would bring people
in and they would show them a pilot for
a new sitcom and tell them you know
we're going to ask you what you thought
of it afterward and people would watch
it and then afterward they would say all
right now there was a question at break
a commercial at break number one which
which average what uh what brand was
this commercial for because they didn't
want people to actually paying attention
to the commercials just to the thing and
they'd used the same sitcom for years
because it was just the test the
commercials because they didn't want
people to be too aware you want to be
like that you want you don't want your
audience who is your writing group to be
aware of what you're planning to do and
if you defend yourself if you ask too
many questions you will predispose them
and you will not get authentic feedback
the best thing you can do is stay quiet
now you are going to ask questions now
and then um trying not to ask too many
questions trying to just write down the
feedback and use it later and this is
you know later is important most new
writers I recommend taking feedback on a
book you finished while you're writing
something else and then coming back to
that feedback month feedback months
later when you're in aevision mindset
reading through it all B making a
revision guide usually I throw out I
take maybe a third of the feedback um
that I'm given um and I have a really
good writing group so you're not going
to take most of it but there's going to
be a lot in there it's going to help you
build this revision guide then you're
going to revise your book and then
you're going to find a new set uh a new
audience and see if you fix the things
that you thought you fixed this will be
really good for you as a new writer
learning to Target at uh people so write
it down if you are Fe giving feedback
last point of
advice be descriptive not prescriptive
did you say it before I got to it you're
cheating you took the class before you
want to describe the piece's impact on
you through words emotion words not you
try to fix their book your job isn't to
fix their book editors fix
books uh beta readers writing groups
just are a test audience so that the
author can tell what people are
authentically feeling as they read the
book so you just say I really enjoyed
this I really enjoyed this um this part
was confusing um I wasn't emotionally
connecting right here I lost blocking
right here not as one as jansy got you
should add rats with swords to the scene
ask her about that if she comes and
teaches the class ever